hello welcome everybody it's November
1st
2023 and we are in the closing
discussion section for
this first instance of active inference
for the social sciences it's been a
journey I'm sure we'll have many fun
things to talk about and explore today
so ail
please take it from here and maybe give
a overview of what we're going to do and
talk about
today okay so this is the uh conclusion
session of our course on active
inference and the for the social science
we have talked extensively about active
inference maybe less extensively about
for the social sense parts so the goal
of the session would be basic to assess
uh what we talked about and how it is
relevant or not to the practice of
social
sciences um basically we will uh this is
a discussion session so there is no
clear plan but I'd like to address uh
how formally active inference accounts
for agency and normativity and identity
as a kind of integrated phenomenon how
it uh can compare or add to or ground or
clash with I don't no a sociological
anthropological model of agency and of
social Evolution and of etc etc all the
topics that we addressed which are
numerous and discuss about the plausible
future for active inference what it can
be used to uh maybe what it will be used
to certainly how it may change and how
it's relevant to the
discussion so um yes that is the um
the uh Crux of it uh we have brought in
Alexi who is a philosopher interested in
Social ontology specifically the study
of social kinds which is from chyos
research and I do not know who colen is
but he's with us hi
Colleen uh so how should we proceed
Danielle do you like what do we
do if you'd like maybe pose a specific
question or prompt
which could be preceded by a statement
and then we can all hear everyone's
voice on
that okay so a good question would be uh
active inference uh describes agency and
Nativity and identity as a kind of um
integrated phenomenon I think we should
go over how precisely it is uh it
works
um so yes let's do that I will uh find
some do you say illustration that will
make it easier but let's hear people's
thought on that
please can you pose your question just a
t more clearly how how are agency
normativity and identity addressed
separately and together in active
inference now go for
it um
so I think we like to look at things in
terms of inter relations in active
inference nothing is defined by itself
it's defined in relation to other things
and this definition in relation to other
things also defines the types of
constraints that will be pushed on the
thing which is separate from other
things um once you have this you
necessitate these inter relationships to
be formative
ontological and um fundamentally
contextual so nothing no
relationship is um perfectly
reproducible across a different context
it will take on a hermeneutics a
semantics given the exact context of the
spatial temporality of the entities um
those are some first thoughts does
anybody have like big objections to what
I I just
[Music]
said
okay so let's
start oh yeah please continue sorry
let's start with the concept of agency
for instance um agency is just action
selection right so uh agents are are are
modeled they have a generative model uh
and they use it to predict like sensory
inputs based on possible actions um they
they chy to select those to minimize the
difference between uh predicted and
sensory inputs
uh so they're just trying to minimize
free energy and this minimization is
fundamentally due to the relationship of
constraints in their environment so
let's imagine that um I am an individual
who
um oh sorry I saw a comment and I
didn't um so yeah so you you uh you have
an individual that tries to exert
control over the environment now if you
scale this in nested structures uh you
can try to think of power structures and
how agency within those power structures
is modulated by the different kinds of
constraints that are both embedded
within the environment itself within the
materiality of the environment and also
within the the normative aspects of the
the nested structures Which pull and
push an individual um within certain
paths through some kinds of Deon CU so
that's how you get to uh the the the
Notions of encoding agents beliefs and
preferences about the world within the
generative model through a form of
normativity which is just a higher
Precision um over a specific type of um
outcome or mapping so uh your your prior
beliefs here come from different layers
in the hierarchy and these act as what
we call culture or normativity um I
could stop here if you want to say
something a so I uh agree with what you
said at a high level conceptual scale
but I think it's important to uh be
clear about what formally the statement
because what we have formally is much
more limited than what we agree the
interpretation could be so can you see
the um the screen I'm
sharing can you see the mouse doing AIDS
yeah okay so at core uh active inference
is a framework uh that provides geometry
for gical systems that is that is not a
very um straightforward to put it but
what we have is a system with a space of
states and uh we have a flow of the
system a flow is a function that
basically tells you where a specific
point goes uh with time and what active
inference says is that given
um yes
given specific patterns of demal
coupling and of statistical dependencies
we have agent like Behavior so the
simplest kind of the basic requirement
of active inference of sorry the
principle which is a core motivation for
active inference is that you have anical
system so something with States and flow
and some noise because we need noise to
get information and it has a boundary in
the middle of it that
um statistically separates the X andol
in states by statistically separate I
mean that every
information uh about what's going on on
there uh that is in there it disappears
when condition on there so information I
have about this that I could read here I
can also read there and that's slly
different fromal coupling but this is
formalism let's not get too much into
this
and then uh you have more complex
behavior when you can partition sensor
in active States and your particle can
do things in this specific context we
can uh write basically we can write a
geometry for the fluctuation of the
system and this geometry it entails
belief of exteral States so this
internal States it knows thing in a
sense about what's going on out there
through its coupling uh through sensory
and active States and the flow it hases
internally the weights internal States
move they entail
um um a displacement of their belief and
this displacement happens to be near
optimal given base constraints blah blah
blah and the real interesting stuff
happens in the case of strange particles
which are particles where uh as you can
see there is no direct effect on of uh
from actions states to internal States
uh the only action you have is mediated
by sensory and external States in this
case uh the active States themselves so
the policy of an agent it becomes uh the
the subject of beliefs of the agent and
if it becomes the subject of beliefs you
can have statistical inference this is
the Crux of the framework and if you can
have cical inference you can have like
quite complex multi-level Cal inference
over re actions and those are basically
what we call decision taking or what we
call planning so um what we have here is
a formal architecture that can derive
the kind of complicated
um agency uh semantic not only agency
but uh agency that is embedded in a
specific conceptual framework that is
relative to the specific structure of an
agent and their environment and the
coupling in between all that is Trace
back basically to Dynamics so we have a
proof of existence that in a world that
everything is aramic we can have agency
we can have complex decision making
under the form of inference over one's
own
actions and then you have complications
to apply it directly of course because
um the world is likely not in its bar
formal system it does not have a list of
states that are
um okay uh there is not a lad of states
that are possible and that's it and
there is one coupling that takes L stes
to themselves and nothing can change
ever this is not likely to be the case
uh but we have a minimal model of agency
that is purely physicalist that is
purely based on Cal relationship in the
most minimal way we can possibly
represent it and this is quite huge and
this tells us this this gives us a very
very strong prior of
what we can what is the stuff that
agency is made of and the stuff that
agency is made of at least higher agency
that we like think about here in the
social context is belief of oneself and
so to control actions is to control
belief of oneself and this is this um
this Duality
this like dual aspect
of uh statistical organization as a
complex cognitive agent that is is in my
opinion at the moment given the
capabilities of modeling informalism we
have the core uh contribution of active
inference to social sciences written
large in Psychology NEOS science like
science of social stuff because it gives
you
a very strong prior over uh what agency
is made of and the kind of stuff that ex
that can exist out there in the social
world and the kind of dynamics that uh
bring about it stuff
so but there is a quite uh big bridge to
be made between the pure demal system
formalism of AC INF frence and the kind
of evolution that happens out there and
I I do think there is um high level of
precaution to be taken when we talk
about this kind of
stuff and yes does anyone want to react
or agree or disagree violently because I
just
attacked the uh common
creeds not sure I perceived an attack
perhaps um from what I understood of
what you said basically um you have
information geometry it formalizes a
belief space in a sort of geometric
manifold uh the points represent
possible belief systems that an agent
can have and uh the distance between the
points in this space can be interpreted
as a measure of how different two belief
systems are and this is
necessarily um tugged by the the the
priors given by the environment which
also push uh uh the agent to act in a
certain way given the type of thing that
it is in order to maintain itself given
the the actions that it knows it has
available um and this becomes normative
because of the um the strength of uh
of of the attractors within the belief
space which become the geometric
landscape basically um so we can sort of
uh model the the the attraction through
the curvature of the of the space around
the attractor and so a high curvature
means a strong normative force uh which
pulls the agent to adopt a certain I
like to say social scripts because
that's what I've worked on but you know
any sort of policy and or phenomenology
Norm um and so in this context the agent
agency is kind of complicated because
it's both um the ability to sort of
navigate the landscape to move closer or
further away from the attractors uh and
so the degree to which an agent has
agency is a degree to which it doesn't
go
necessarily um directly towards the
attractor but has some degree of
reflexivity over its own um action space
in order to navigate that uh the the
different kinds of
um uh tractors that may be available to
it uh so we could see that the momentum
would be like affected by uh personal
experiences education in Tendencies uh
or even you know the tendency to to
resist or yield um to uh to social
pressures I could go on but I know that
um a you have your hand up so why don't
you
go uh okay uh
I guess a could answer before before I
talk a bit so I was just trying to have
my hand raised
before um yeah before talking so if ever
wants to ansers you and afterwards I can
talk
uh I'm okay I don't have anything
specific to
answer okay
okay uh so you you talked about the dual
aspect of statistical organization of
complex
agent uh and you said that was a core
contribution of active influence to
social
sciences um can you dig a bit on that
um and yeah Ju Just articulate it a bit
more so we could grasp it
better and then I could uh ask questions
if so do I still share my screen uh yes
so basically what we uh what we have in
here
is a formalism that um that builds from
very basic Dynamics in like just space
and there is stuff that to paace zero
level physical presentation of literally
anything can go there and uh from there
we build a model of first uh self
organization not quite that agentive
self organization let us say something
that can build a specific stable ecology
and maintain itself in this ecology that
is what we have here and then uh given
the lack of coupling between active and
to States we can build uh sensibly more
complex stuff that can Implement uh
higher order beliefs about themselves
and what they do and uh like do decision
making that is condition and information
they have about themselves and
planification under the form of uh
beliefs over their own action
and as such this is like this is just
math this says nothing about the world
in and of itself until we claim it
corresponds to things in the world and
we can claim that uh this is a basic
conceptual model that Maps well on
culturation basically social
organization engagement with the social
cultural world because then we can
account of uh the human ability for very
very very um
white open-ended learning as something
that comes from there as something that
allows us to infer things about
ourselves and then develop complex
policies and knock them blah blah blah
and because to my knowledge there is no
competing model that that comes for
anything near that like
the the only competition like the
competition I should not talk of
competition but the um the other models
of um cognitive organization curation
that exist that are trying to ground
themselves in physics like Nal system
they are just talking about Dynamics
they are specifically avoiding talking
about anything like content of or
semantics so the facto this piece of
math as a monopoly on building semantics
from the ground and what it tells you is
that agency and identity and relativity
it's all the same phenomenon it's
conditioned by a self-belief basically
that is constructed in this specific way
and we can um how to say because this is
the only way that we can account for
higher order
agency then we have we at least I would
argue we have we should have a strong
priors for uh theories of agency either
mechanical or uh conceptual that Vibe
well with that picture so this is the
claim I'm making I guess I want to too
much detail so I hope this is
enough okay um okay so I have some maybe
not questions but some points to make
now um thank
you um so from what I see here uh we
could put the active influence Paradigm
into the
individualistic uh methodological
individualism
um framework in sociology so the idea is
that you try to model an individual and
then uh when you have the good way to
model the individual you can generalize
to what everyone is doing so for
instance um if I'm working on something
uh in certain way then I could
generalize about that and say uh okay
sociologically uh I have this constraint
to work on this uh stuff and then not
like everyone is doing that but it could
goes like that but what is interesting
here is that it's not only about one
individual but also that uh for instance
let's let's take the external State you
could say that external States here or
other agents and also
that
um okay so you have the active state in
the internal state so we could say that
your internal states are totally
influenced by another agent so we could
do something like that with the two
individuals I guess so one is one of the
agent here and the other Drive the
internal states of the model because
they are really influential on
uh on
yourself but so there are some
limitations on about this kind of way of
thinking because in general
um in sociology or in sociological
Sciences what you would like to say is
that there are some agents at a higher
level than only individuals such as you
and I so the trick could be to say that
some states for instance or some firms
or agents uh for and by themselves so
you have agent which are not individual
persons uh about you talko social
scripts
I don't understand what you tried to say
a
um I was just trying to react to your
your
slide
um because I don't see how it connects
with my own work here yet oh I'm talking
to M okay nice
um so yeah if if Mar you have something
to say about what I just said about how
we could have let's say two active
agents uh trying to talk together
uh yeah so um we we have such
simulations that already exist um over
various kinds of scales we have um two
agents
coordinating um that are animals like
birds singing and overtime coordinating
over the song they're going to sing uh
we have uh several models of leader
follower where um you have one agent two
agents starting from relatively the same
point but one agent developing more
confidence and therefore developing a
dynamic of leader follower with the
other agent this is work that's possibly
um going to be followed uh by Francisco
Balan who is working on um models of
education and how maybe the teacher and
student and dynamic may be cast under
these terms um I've done work with Axel
constant and maxel ramstead in terms of
um active inference in social scripts
that's that's what AA was mentioning and
this notion that um through the cues of
the environments your own model is
shaped both by the environment which
includes other people and the way in
which you self evidence within this
environment so for instance
um there's two ways we can understand
your question first like we can say that
um U minimizing free energy um is
basically an agent that has a form of
autonomy and it's constantly updating
its model to align with the environment
so by virtue of doing this it's not
fundamentally individual but um that
each agent has its own model of the
world each agent reflects a perspective
a very unique moment in SpaceTime that
will um that will incur some errors
relative to others so it's not that they
necessarily interpreted things wrong
although they might have but um because
their perspective is slightly off from
somebody else there's necessarily a
degree of incommunicability in this
sense um so here self- evidencing really
entails that uh um identity you create a
sort of identity here through the fact
that you uh you may have different
preferred States from somebody else
based on your values belief your social
conditioning but again these beliefs and
values and social conditioning have been
shaped and and um again we're talking
about these 12 of attractors by other
people um and so we try more and more to
challenge this notion of individualism
by emphasizing the relational aspect of
identity um which is which means that
identity is not pre-established but
continuously formed uh through the
interaction with other agents uh and
again if we go back to information
geometry the the the the geometry of the
information space influences how agent
perceive their paths towards minimizing
free energy and affect their choices
which again give you uh the possibility
to understand um how agents might be
very strongly pushed by other agents
let's imagine an agent that has more
power than you and is uh trying to
influence you to do something someone
that has very high Charisma or someone
who has the power to say destroy your
life you are more likely to shape your
belief beliefs to align
with and therefore we can understand
individualism under a very very
different light here um AAL did you want
to add
something Colleen is waiting to speak
since a moment so let's see
Colleen
hi I can you hear
okay I just I just wanted to pick on a
couple of the things that Mah was
talking about um and just now and in her
in her talk it seems that uh the you you
seem to be saying that that for social
conditioning and the way in which we are
socialized uh the the importance of
social scripts appears to be greater
than the influence of individual upon uh
individual and that's interesting
because it's not something that we would
tend to think as individuals that we are
we are integrating the scripts in fact
the the whole idea of seeing a script as
something which is social uh was
something that I found that probably
most people would find uh a rather
strange idea um off the off the top of
our heads so so yeah that uh is that a
fair is that a fair assessment of what
you're trying to say and the other thing
I wanted to ask about was uh a few times
uh in in talks recently and here today
um I've heard people talking about
identity and the active inference view
of uh of identity I'm not sure that I
really understand what identity means
within an active inference framework as
distinct from just our internal model of
who we are uh is there an other is there
an other idea that we are we are uh we
are we're thinking of here and more
particularly the word identity has a lot
of baggage and usage in current
contemporary Society um are we using it
in a different way uh and if so how is
it different and potentially how does
that give us insight and the ability to
engage with the ongoing discussions in
society in a potentially fruitful
way so I I think I lost you for the last
part of your question which seemed to be
about the difference between our
conception of identity and the the
conception generally used if that's uh
that's
correct
you're muted
calling sorry yeah I was I was referring
to the concept of identity as used in
society
um right so I mean I'm not going to
speak to every use of the term identity
because it's a very very useful term
that's used in law that's used in
physics it's used in sociology and
psychology so it's used a lot um all I
can do is explain roughly how we
consider identity formation and then if
you have a specific definition in mind
for a specific field we can maybe tackle
that one does that sound um okay yeah um
to be clear I was thinking specifically
about identity as determined by group
membership in sociology
um okay um okay so I'm going to tackle
social scripts first yeah um um I'm
going to tackle social scripts first and
then I'm going to come back to identity
because I think it fits I've worked on
that as well I know that Daniel and a
have some work that relates to this as
well but so your first question was um
on the importance of social scripts and
what it means for cognition if I
understood uh correctly so from an
internalist
perspective
um social scripts are cognitive
structures they guide behaviors they're
they're acting like um brackets we use
the word constraints a lot it's it's not
a perfect um it's not a perfect guide
because no semantic marker is a perfect
guide everything is up for some degree
of interpretation it's just that there
are some interpretations they're
so strongly linked to some degree of
embodiment that they sort of anchor the
rest of our semantics so for instance I
can't stop breathing if I wanted to CH I
I have I will stop but eventually my
body will restart on its own um and so
there's there's such kinds of natural
laws here that um create these these um
bottom layer guidelines that can then be
sort of derived to infer other things
and social scripts are just a
representational
um social extensions of these
constraints given a historical context
so um they model uh
and did M drop or did ey
drop I guess it's given to you like
somebody will actually tell you what to
do and show it to you um and sometimes
they won't be sometimes they are just
things You observe sometimes there's
things you infer because you made a
connection between a week script and
another week script so if you see
something that resembles a chair in a
room you infer that you have the
affordance to sit on it so that's a form
of script then you see other people
doing the same in the script sort of
cements and so now um You you associate
this to another part of a sequence and
this becomes something that's um that
allows you to temporize um and and
basically leverage your B Matrix in
order to exist in the world in a way
that doesn't cause friction with other
people this also gives you action
triggers there are things you see in the
world that now tell you this is the
thing you should do now so there's this
sort of um recursive Loop that's very
inactive that pulls you in a Direction
so the the the attractor isn't just a
state it's a path you're going to go
down a path um so for now is that does
that answer the first
question yes thanks that's
helpful okay uh
go
ahead thank you uh to get back on the
like you talked about the active Loop
and I think that's a critical thing to
underline which is that the engagement
with the world is a cyclic process a
circular process it construct its own
conditions uh and the so there is no
measure of power of structure versus
Power of Agents because the structure is
embedded in the agents and the agents
are embedded in the structure so I I'd
like to share my screen
again uh to give some detail over what
this entails do I can I yes good window
you should see a PDF with a tiny man a
personal Mon and
Loops is it okay it's
okay yes I see yes so this is a
presentation I did recently about the uh
unification Church which is uh like when
you want to be uh published you say new
religious movement but you can say cult
it works uh which originated I think in
Japan and is now spread between Korea
Japan it says mostly we don't have
numbers but it seems uh to be the places
where it's most
implanted and it was very very very um
remarked because of the personal cult
around the Reverend Moon the founder and
the Very overt exactive practices of the
cult like asking you for the equivalent
of 10 years of salary at the time to
uh and to take your ancestors from hell
and put them in Paradise by giving money
to R Moon
specifically and
they they were the topic of a very um I
say aggressive and excessive anticult
movement in the 70s 80s and now they are
becoming a bit noticed Again by Vice uh
not only Vice but notably Vice because
you have very strange strange things
like Mass Maga weddings with people
waving rifle and that is a very strange
organization and at the time you had the
very um moral Panic with say know around
the cult uh you had you had basically a
model of influence that was that evil
people would brainwash you and then you
were commanded by the cult and our
Soviet secret agents from afar and they
could like say to you horse and is
triggered uh homos cidal Mania in which
you blah blah blah so things that are
unnatural istic I will say and uh
notably in reaction to the moral Panic
you had a movement by solist of religion
that would try to understand how exactly
cult worked and the most famous
sociologist to do that was aen Barker if
I remember well she uh like she was she
warned the moies she was coming so you
can question her
methodology uh but she seems to have
done the most thorough and uh well
received analysis of them so it's quite
important thing and she questions that
there is such a thing as brainwashing
there is a construction of a specific
social context that you have to comply
to if you want to come but they can
force you they they do not have the
capability to uh like torture you and
make you into a RC radio Community thing
that's that that does not work and so I
forgot the name of the so David Frank
Taylor uh explained uh the influence of
the church in terms of choreography of
to participation so basically you have
very huge very um emotionally investing
ritual that have you just have to take
part in to be a member of the community
and if you are a member of the community
you will be helped you will be loved you
will be supported you will be uh
constantly encouraged in a slightly
coercive way to uh invest more of your
time and money and whatever in the
organization
and if you don't then all this sport
just leaves because you know you're a
traitor you you you have you have uh
done uh treason of the true parents who
will Who was kindly out of his own art
trying to uh save you like Jesus did but
better because Jesus failed by not
having children that's that is very
dramatic thing to say that is what they
said and because of the way the
organization is set up there is you you
cannot possibly question that your
questioning is not accepted there is no
private time in which you can privately
question yourself you are always engage
with people who are either uh formally
or informally depending on your
seniority watching you and so you have
basically a context that makes it very
very very easy to align with the uh cult
values and it just happens that those
values they they entail self-sacrifice
for the organization but also for new
members and uh total difference to the
cult and its leadership and anything
they tell you to do so you you know it's
not nothing but it's also not exactly
free consent to a specific context and
from a purely uh I don't know what to
say mechanical perspective they can they
can make you agree when you are there
but they cannot make you go there so a
question is how precisely they can you
know elicit a compliance away from the
direct context of the choreography of
participation and there is a like simple
answer in my which is that U we have we
have a coherent sense of identity we
can't we can hardly think ourselves as a
good money one minute and then step out
of the meeting and not think of
ourselves as a good money that doesn't
make sense either we are or we are not
at least most people tend to have one
integrated sense of themselves as
someone who is embedded in a specific
social context and specific norms and
behaves in such such way and so the uh
the coherence of self-identity it
provides a key coupling between your
public and your private beliefs what you
are expected to do in Social context and
what you will effectively do and
perceive the world as privately and this
I would say uh in the example of theonis
but in other rhetorical examples like uh
the emergence of nationalism it is a
very straightforward confirmation that
indeed coherence of self-identity like
the coherence between what you do and
what you think of yourself as doing is a
very important process in the uh in the
structure of societies generally
speaking at least contemporary societies
maybe it was not the same before Al so I
do not think like the context in which
it's mobar of course it changes but the
mechanism I don't think it's new and I'd
like to get back on Alexis's point that
um sorry A's Point that's uh the
approach we have is
um individualistic I I do not think it
is the case because if we are correct uh
there is a landscape of social cultural
afford dencies
constraints uh things world out there
and we engage with it and there are
mechanism that makes this landscape not
necessarily identical but very coherent
between individuals and those mechanism
are language and the material symbolism
developing ritual which is also
symbolism also meaningful but maybe less
than language I don't know uh I just
mean that the mechanism is the same and
uh the um interculturally robust
practice of Ro taking and uh Shar
intentionalities are trying to do stuff
together um given a
specific uh model of the attribution of
tasks within the shared uh goal and so
these are human EnV variants and all
would be pretty good candidate to force
the integration of a common model of
material and cultural Niche and
so I think that there is a pretty
coherent soci material nich I think that
uh we can we all engage with it and we
all modify it and we maybe do not
perceive it as the same but there is
still a strong enough constraints uh on
the coherence of this landscape between
individuals for it to make sense as a
specific entity and then the proper
respiratory scale of what we do is not
the individual Minds it is lscape that
we happen to experience because of our
minds so by the um PL uh Plateau
Academia of Stanford on holism basically
holism is a theory where you agree that
there are uh explanation that are not
mediated by IND States and I say there
are explanation that are not invented by
IND States
and not only that but I can point
organization that control people while
being absolutely not worried about
indidual states only creating a ccum
text and then allowing them to engage
with it and that would be compelling in
my opinion to say that the model we have
is Maybe not holist maybe a secret third
thing that is multiscale but certainly
not individualist at least in the sense
that you are
mobilizing so thank you uh I talked more
than I wanted so
you were raising your hands I am but I
think Lorena wants to go I will go after
Lorena hey guys uh yeah I think that
goes like directly into the idea that
coming a little back coming back a
little bit to the point that identity
they were talking before and if you
think about the model that we have uh we
have external the external States and
different agents they are always
actually very local in situated in the
same
um in the same local constrainted local
environment right so your external agent
is going is going to be part uh other
agents are going to be part of your
external States and you are part of
theirs right so the idea of like laying
down a path and creating a specific type
of
dynamic that react to the same type of
input that you're receiving and driving
these
Dynamics will generate this sort of
embeddedness right because you do create
you do have the
same um or it's not necessarily the same
but they're very very close to each
other they're very approximate right so
the idea of a dynamic here if you think
about uh describing that in terms of
um place and like in terms of Dynamics
you do have very different like um
Lauren but butterflies for instance each
one goes through the same type of Route
however they're not identical but
they're very similar they are doing
something very similar and that
similarity sort of constraints again uh
the construction of that environment so
if you think about symbols and roles and
uh types of environment that you find
they're going to be as concrete as
something else that you find in your
environment constraining and pushing you
towards the same direction or at least a
very similar uh you can describe
dynamically in a very similar type of
geometry if you if you like or a very
similar or this attractor will drive the
very similar type of uh path we describe
this similar type of path so which goes
exactly to the uh a can you go back to
that um other
um yeah the the other figure that you
have the one with the envir M as
well made by yeah that one so that
exactly that creates like a dynamic that
they can be then for
forgotten like in a way that will be
described through a a specific Mar of
blank that will
develop agents uh together we push them
constraining they're going to be
constrained together and they're going
to have a
constructive kind of
um role in this embedded uh In This Very
embedded
normativity but yeah you go
a thanks um yes so I think there's a
nice way to tie all this as well to the
internal nature that we seem to be um
dispelling but we're not we like we have
to talk about specifically in what ways
internality is cast here and um I like
to think of that the the effect of
self-esteem here self-esteem to me is
the degree of Fitness relative to your
perception of how well you are managing
to exist Within These constraints and
interpret them in a way that gets other
people to validate and and minimize the
friction that you're getting from other
people so uh it it it aligns with the
concept of sociometer theory it Taps
into this notion of cult um
so if you consider that there's
effective states that enable an
individual to track and respond to
discrepancies between
self-perception and social expectation
through these effective states such as
um anxiety or positive affect um we can
see that there's a dynamic nature and
self-organization of self-esteem which
is continually shaped and reshaped by
experiences and
interactions um and so uh under activ
inference we can formalize this by
saying that a model uh that is more
precise uh effectively captures the
higher cool structure of the moment to
moment variation of more stable traits
such as uh what we consider to be
self um and so
basically um we can see that identity
and group membership here are
fundamentally related to the effective
experience of um Being Fit for the group
membership and so once you're there you
you can grow in Social cohesion and this
will lead you to potentially try to
maintain the group it will try to it
will lead you to try to justify the
beliefs of the group such that uh you
have a form of confirmation bias but
also you maintain the epistemic reality
of this group The symbolic reality of
this group which would be more costly to
destroy than to actually uh support it's
also
integrated into your self-esteem
therefore destroying the group would
mean admitting that you are potentially
not fit for the environment that you are
uh potentially some degree of wrong um
and so this this um this leads us to the
possibility that if someone has low
self-esteem what do they do they can
either stay in this group and accept
that they are unfit for the group uh and
they they would try to remove themselves
to some extent from the group to avoid
all that friction
or they can try to join a different
group one which will support uh your
beliefs about the world if your beliefs
are too far from where the the group
you're supposed to belong to currently
is and this is where we get to these
subclusters forming these little uh
subgroups uh that potentially can even
become um sometimes violent and
sometimes really not sometimes it's just
you know some tumbler group but um it it
has power because it gives the
individual this feeling this veillance
um of now being fit to a group that
supports their
model so I wanted to give AA space to
talk yes thank you um so I would like to
go back a bit uh on what I said about uh
individualism so yeah I agree that uh I
was wrong about associating active
insurance with individualism because
what is interesting here is that there
is an individuality through active
inference which emerg from uh the
collective and you can justify or
describe uh individ idual actions or
else through the L uh through the
landscape as you did just now and then
go the other way around so we here we
seems we seem to grasp the interaction
between the individual in the group and
vice
versa uh which is what I found
interesting here
um uh and okay more moreover there's the
what the individual adds to a group uh I
see that here it seems to be captured as
we take the individual as
a um how to say that uh a unique
perspective this is what you said before
ma uh
that uh each person is a perspective uh
a unique one and yeah uh it's not all
what I wanted to say also uh yeah Lorena
you talked about the the beliefs that
exist and I think this uh this is one
interesting thing also in active
infrance it's that we take belief as a
material thing that uh influences us and
that we can also influence or create in
a way um even yeah independently of if
it's right wrong or whatever we we judge
it is like
uh what we talked about with the moon
sect uh and the the unification Church
yeah so there are people with crowns and
we say that they are the big boss and we
have to deal with it or to go away from
the landscape and from the landscape and
yeah it works like that in the social
world indepently of if the person is
really the like the the the chief of the
Cults or or not because they said the
words and people were just following
them so in the end it happened to create
a landscape in which the in which one
person is
the
uh the the person who has power so yeah
I don't know what to say more about all
of this I guess I agree with with what
you said just before so
yeah that's it
so maybe we should move to like
challenges and opportunities of active
inference uh
so uh two points I think like I just put
them out there you can
react um I think that one active
influence may give us computational
models or even like thorough gred
conceptual
models of social organization
specifically
the like semantic Dimension to social
life and I also think that in its
current formulation within the M System
Theory it is inapt to represent par
Evolution because M system entail the
formulation of set of states that do not
change through time and AAL flow that
does not either change FL time so there
is there are opportunities to apply the
model
to the framework to uh
grounded meaningful semantically
complete models of soci evolution but
this model if that come for evolution
they will not really Vibe well with the
math that we invoke to say our
computational model are meaningful and
that's like rise and AR R of questions I
guess so yeah does anyone want to react
to these two
statements
could I go sorry could I could I make a
comment um
just more more specifically I'm I'm I'm
interested in the in the ways in which
uh the ideas of active influence impact
on the way we think about society and
the way Society Works uh and I I can see
from from my reading and from listening
to the disc discussion that there's a
very rich du lexicon in vocabulary a set
of concepts for the thinking within
active inference uh thought and as we
just as we just commented it's quite
heavily mathematical so the barrier to
entry uh for for for the full active
inference uh um worldview is
is over time these ideas will will re
will permeate out into the mainstream
and they will change the way people
think and talk about Society I I'm
interested in the ways people who've
studied a bit more than than than I have
see potentially how this will change the
way Society works or the way that uh the
way that we we uh we have disc we have
discussions or Envision Society more
widely than just an academic discussion
obviously um maybe the question is a bit
too
big I mean I think I think everyone is
just waiting for the other to talk first
talked first
so um so I I I think I want to tackle a
little bit what you said about um the uh
the open-ended uh
nature uh the open-ended Evolution uh of
of um of State spaces
basically um I think under the path
formulation um this open-endedness is
actually just a perceived
open-endedness it's just um a function
of uh the time scale being considered
and the motion along that time
scale
um I think uh I think we can go a little
bit more into depth about this um I
think it's a very large topic like
effectively um if we go into Quantum
formulations there's um some degree of
irreducibility and anything above that
is historically contingent so obviously
some things will some Mark of blankets
will dissolve and reform and dissolve
and reform and through this dissolution
and Reformation uh you get a new
potential for mapping of observation to
States so there's there's always that
possibility um but I think some
challenges um for active inference that
are
coming uh is for instance uh the the
complexity of social behavior um you
know we we um we can extand active
inference to capture the nuances of
social
interactions uh but effectively active
inference is about you know abduction so
it's the best guess for now um and it
requires for us to put into the
models uh what we think are useful
variables what we think are the right
variables um and it's
possible that we're always going to fall
just a little bit short like we're
always we can either throw a bunch of
data at a problem and be like okay well
just just remove the noise only pick up
the signal and figure out what's
happening but that's no better than than
big data deep learning so um we have to
figure out a way to move forward and
understand the the variables of interest
and do this across scales so identify
the priors that take over at a given
moment but they won't take over even if
they're higher in the hierarchy at
another moment because in this hierarchy
you've actually switched States like
you've moved uh and this is only
predictable uh once you've understood
the effect of those PR PR um you can
just consider that you have the priors
to begin with
um so yeah as far as uh uh integration
with existing theories I think we have a
nice opportunity ahead of us it's what
it's basically what you said um Colin I
think we're going to be able to more and
more through um the alignment of certain
kinds of language and the
formalism um under that language we're
going to be able to pull more and more
theories and find what's at the core of
the connection between these theories
active inference is supposed to be
scale-free so it describes or it is
possible to help us describe the
phenomena basically from sociology and
literature to biology so if we
understand this we understand that
there's a possible touch point a
convergence of all these fields that are
tapping into to the same ideas or into
some connecting points that allow us to
understand how we maybe do away with
these um different fields remove the
silos and come back together with
something that feels more integrative um
but then again we're back to the
computational limits obviously like if I
want to compute um the prediction for an
entire country what is the granularity
level at which I I should compute the
the right variable and if we understand
that uh individuals are formed by the
group Etc do I just do a mean field over
the entire group in which case am I
losing out on some of the variables that
may actually impact the outcomes um I
think these are the the key questions
that remain to be answered to some
extent so I agree with the what you said
now
um I I agree with that we
can't like represent things and not
somehow not cut anything relevant to the
thing when we model or we represent the
point of it is to have a more compressed
way to engage with the thing with our
knowledge of the thing than the actual
thing so we will just cut information
that is the point of modeling or
representing and uh maybe in a very
simple system such like um
just say perfect gas model in physics
there is information we can cut and lose
nothing we can uh cut information about
which particle is where because the
different particles of the same atom as
at this scale the same properties so we
don't really care where atom what what
Atom does what but in the case of human
societies we have like patterns of
Engagement and the like specific
information that is accessed by spe
agent is important important and
whatever we choose to cut for a model it
will be relevant at some point at least
it will probably be if like the
information we cut uh is not specific to
a bunch of agent that will die of car or
something uh if any kind of information
any type of information we may want to
abstract out will be relevant somewhere
at some point so we yeah we we are
dealing with complex systems we are not
going to model everything but I
it is it is it is a huge deal that
active inference is capable to fill in
the semantic content from Dynamics
either from like the Dynamics of a
component system say neural Dynamics and
biological Dynamics or dynamics of a
social context with um the modeling of
act influence agent as a like things
that navigate the world and make
inference and stuff and to my knowledge
we do not have any other theory that
makes the bridge between like just
Dynamics and
semantics and we have other neurological
like cognitive Neuroscience people who
talk about Dynamics a lot and how we can
bring back uh the activity of cognitive
systems to Dynamics but usually it is um
it is in a way that insists that we we
should just look at the Dynamics we
don't really need to worry about the
semantics or if we need to worry about
the semantics they somehow like reduce
to the Dynamics the Dynamics is what
exists and is important and what we
should worry
about and so another framework that is
relevant to like just study evolution of
norms or presentation or mental content
in a context I don't I cannot think of
one one that is Thoroughly grounded in a
at least that that attempts to
thoroughly ground itself in mathematics
mathematical physics I yeah there is the
isent another one and so that is a huge
deal but there is a very important
problem which is what you what I said
and you said and we which is that the
paress in the path integral formulation
in only ofation in the FP it is illusory
it is about like it uh so maybe to give
a bit of context uh the path integral
formulation of the FP is just when you
do the FP so the of math we make huge
deal about and we uh apply it not to uh
like the Dynamics of a particle per se
like how it affects a particle at Point
T but how it affects pathes of a
particle for mathematic reasons uh
reframing a problem in path integral
formulation is a huge deal it is what
what makes the difference between a
Newtonian you push something and it
moves and full-fledge quantum go
theories that uh underwrite all of
contary
physics uh so yeah path integral
formulation is a huge deal but to write
it you still need to write an AIC space
like to make the list of all thing that
are possible and like if
you if you think that there this is a
correct model of the world and a
complete model of the world and this is
everything there is you have to agree
either that caes do not exist
or that there is a place in the Primo
web function that existed before
Universe did before time did there is a
place where con lies and I think Co
exist and I do not think Co are basic
properties of quantum mechanics So Co
must have happened along the way somehow
and to represents that mean to
represents
upness and so we need upness in math and
the FP is not one ended and it like
structurally it's very hard to account
forend evolution
and at a more praic level when we look
at engagement with the social dynamics
with the social world we look at piness
because there is always a integration of
norms there is always a loss of
information but also that is
constructive of new Norms there is no
like writing happen at some point and
then we did things differently it
changed the structure of socities it
enabled Administration to exist as a
non-trivial uh C power Society that's
actually mattered in its organization
and
yeah so new things happen and if we want
to look at social engagement it is
critical to look at how new things
happen and currently the FP doesn't do
that and active INF frence I don't think
it does that maybe maybe it can at a
computational level without uh Grand
from all pretention maybe but I did not
see it and that's a big challenge that
we have ahead of us and by we I mean
everyone not just AC INF frence people
everyone should de a that at some point
Daniel you were raing your hand I I I'll
add just a few notes to Colin's question
certainly it's something that we all ask
ourself and many viewers and
participants in the ecosystem ask like
so what what then what does it really
mean for active inference to
be applied to or by or in the social
science so I think that's a big open
question certainly one that's not only
addressable by one perspective or even
with words alone but I think there's a
few key pieces especially that
differentiate it from just the broader
or adjacent project of quantitative
social science or formal social science
the the question we should seek after is
what does active inference bring in and
again probably many ways to say it but
we know for an active inference agent as
as as a
scale-free
statement free energy can be bounded by
changing the world or changing the mind
so having continuity of social systems
with all other systems spatial temporal
arbitrary material and so on gives a
continuity in an
interoperability that without a
scale-free first principles approach is
essentially not even on the radar so
that's one massive piece and then I
think where that begins to bear or
modify fruit is essentially the
scientific and professional development
of cognitive
engineering understanding that the
cognitive constraints and scaffolds
scripts all of these tasks implicitly
and then more recently explicitly and
most recently quantitatively and
formally are examples of cognitive
engineering so whether it's a stop sign
and what that comes to mean in different
social locations or or language as a
complex phenomena these are examples of
cognitive Engineering in the same way
that building a stack of rocks is both
an example of material engineering and
cognitive engineering through semiotics
and now when the scientific process the
professional
process enters into this reflexive and
relational posture through active
inference
that is kind of a saddle point into a
different Dynamic I believe
Lena Lorena unmute and then go for
it yeah I just make uh one comment what
you said like keep in mind that active
inference can understand beliefs and
signs and this kind of of
um semiotics as material and concrete
because constraints they constraint the
evolution of the system like how the
system complexifies right and the
constraints are materi has this material
uh effect on the Dynamics right you
cannot really um believe that of course
belief is materialized as a table of
course not but for the system in terms
of constraining and understanding how
things is SC and how they complexify
they have that um kind of role and that
helps to understand a little bit what
Val was bringing about how you can bring
new uh values and parameters for the
Dynamics that are being described by the
mathematics of external and internal
free energy principle uh updating right
and that is a way of tackling this um
novelty for this kind of um this kind of
thinking over time but we don't have a
proper account on how to how to
predict what is going to constrain the
the system
last
right yeah Ma go for it and then we'll
all kind of give a closing round slash
thoughts okay well there was a um a
question in the chat uh at one point so
I just wanted to potentially address the
question if that's uh if that's okay um
so the question was so would the
generative process of modeling the
social system enclose multiple agents on
one uh Mark of blanket or I assume
inside or under one mark of blanket so
we like to think of active inference as
nested in hierarchical that's one thing
that Maxwell ramstead definitely
pioneered uh where each agent has its
own uh Mark of blankets but there is a
higher level Mark of blanket that
encloses the the social system in play
so individual agents can interact with
each other and the environment but the
social system as a whole also interacts
with the broader environment and this is
where where semantics and semiotics come
into play uh and the the narratives
around certain groups start shaping how
they can interact with the other groups
which have a perception of these
narratives so there's ingroup and
outgroup
Dynamics so it's a uh so it's a little
bit again to how cells within an
organism have their own boundaries but
are also part of a larger um
organism um
so yeah I think that that does that
answer the question from the person who
asked that
question think ites nice
so perhaps a and
Colin feel free to give in your marks
and then we'll pass around the
instructors it can be as long or as
short as you like yeah okay may I go
yeah uh first
so uh I would like to say that uh the
the key issue we are like uh trying to
to grasp is that effective inference uh
has social and political implications
due to its
scale-free structure and how we can
apply to to the social world then there
is the self referential question that
happens which is what is the the what is
the the structure of active influence as
a social construction itself and a
political construction itself
and what are our own
um like our
own what what is our own political power
and Social Power in this social and
political world and this is the like the
fact like thing that is going on like
because afterward what is my own social
and political implication in this thing
and the more you you get your own agency
and the agency of active influence the
more it becomes like a lot to to process
and uh the more you you you grasp your
own agentivity and um and the power you
have and the how to say that
responsibility
yeah you you have so yeah I guess this
is one of the key points we're trying to
to to get
here um yeah uh I guess that's the the
point I I wanted to make and yeah to to
finish with that
um we the the the game we are trying to
play is to to try to find our own blind
spots in this game like what is the
limit of the model
and does it have a self referential
limit or not so
yeah that's
it yeah I would um I would Endor that
and um that was yeah I feel the same way
I I found that uh my reading of of in
just in the last year or so of of active
inference ideas I found it very
empowering uh the ideas of of active
inference in in relation to the the
individual mind uh are quite
welldeveloped and um it's yeah very
empowering to be able to look at
yourself through the active inference
Paradigm and understand the thought
processes that is you uh it's a very
empowering thing and uh as uh as I was I
was saying just just recently starting
to look at the idea that we can
incorporate an active inference concept
of the way the social world around us is
structured which is part of that
Paradigm too I think is uh is
potentially more empowering but uh it's
early days yet uh but I look forward
very much to uh a more developed world
where um people have discussions with
each other not just about what I'm
thinking and how I think but how I think
about society and how we think about
Society together and it's embedded
within that uh with that within that
Paradigm I feel that's potentially
something which is very imp powering and
I and I look forward to it and and I
thank the speakers all for their
contributions to this uh this series of
talks thank you Colin so with the
exception of Ben whose lecture and
contribution kicked off this course and
were excellent also we have the
others of the instructors here so how do
each of you want to uh kind of conclude
this
chapter yeah
Ma Ben L
Rael yes I think
uh
of entities which have the capability of
interacting to maximize the information
they gather from the environment such
that as a whole they can self evidence
to um maintain the phenotypes they
believe to be similar to their own and
therefore their themselves um and how
this leads to over time the
sedimentation of norm nors and
activities and eventually the reference
to these norms and activities through
the semantics and the scripts um and
effectively how this leads us to all the
the complexities of language and how we
may now be at the point where we have a
simulacra that represents nothing it's
just we just have these um these shells
of representations and these shells of
semantics uh which potentially have lost
their anchoring in reality so I think
that was the the through line of the
course I hope we made a good case for it
and how active inference allows us to
model this entire path not only across
scale but across time as well um so yeah
that's how I think uh I'm going to
close yeah I think this is me now yeah I
I really like the the story as well that
we are building throughout the whole uh
course starting with a very general idea
of what is active inference with Ben and
then trying to like build up this
Collective notion how we how we contain
information in a certain way that it's
always synchronized so this is always
sort of meaningful that can be described
in certain in C Ways by the mathematics
of active inference and then
understanding these questions hard
questions that we asking now like how we
can bring new variables how can bring
novelty into the system which something
that we don't have an answer yet but I
find that's really cool that we don't
like hold back in asking that because
that I think this that's the next step
for AC like understanding this how
complexification comes about how can we
describe that process and yeah and
thanks sael and Daniel for putting this
together was pretty cool and I hope you
guys also have
enjoyed
thank you
Lorena
AEL so uh thank you L you're
welcome uh I think uh the put his finger
on uh something quite
deep as uh as usual which is that if we
want to have a coherent theory of nature
that is not based on just here are the
thing that can be and we we'll draw that
that that um is compatible with OP
Evolution we need to address self fality
we need to address like um not compal
but um
recursion and the the possibility for
recursive individuation of physical
beings and that's tough and that's very
tough because the the the the basis of
presentation is just at list uh array of
things I want to represent and I
represent that but if things can just
happen that are new and that are by
definition not in the field of
possibilities that preexisted then we we
we we are there is no way we can
represent that and uh there is there is
um a fam of approach in Quantum
information theory that tries to tackle
that how to draw physics without
um um being rolling in a specific St
space and just I'd like to to to to expl
explain the history of that so the math
it draws from algebraic topology so we
study surfaces but not by studying
surfaces by setting transformation
within those surfaces but then we remove
the surfaces and we keep only the
transformation over what I don't know
but somehow we can I guess
reconstruct uh coherent mathematical
entity from that and I'd like us to take
a look at how this look what the math
look like
so can you can we see the screen okay so
this is the structure of the quantum
information formulation of the FP uh
these
are dimension of interaction between
system a and system B uh what defines
the scope and the mode of this
interaction I don't know and this is a
con coone diagram that represent an
agent together with the representation
that he develops and I could tell you
the words that correspond to the thing
within this diagram but I do not know
what they mean so it would be a hard
thing to do and the math that is capable
to tackle the self fality like maybe
because I I did not see any proof that
it actually does in fact it's it's not
tractable for humans and I exclude
mathematical physics for from humans
there because of the abstractness of
what is going on and because of the lack
of any abuse reference that from
anything we in understand in this and
the work that we have to do if we want
this to move forward and to have a
self-coherent theory of social evolution
is to somehow entangle from that um
concrete meaning things that apply to
the world and conversely use the way
that we can think of it as concrete
inter ction in the world to further
specify the mathematics and prove that
it is actually self-coherent and applies
to stuff and this is a big big work uh
in fact and this is kind of exciting I
guess what I wanted to say is uh active
inference is dead Long Live active
inference great
well it was a fun course and this
closing section and slide kind of
brought this Unity between Chris
fields's
Quantum work and this social science
which in the disciplinary Paradigm are
seen as distant or with different
systems of interest and you can't get
there from here but in a scale-free
first principles Paradigm it's not even
just that we can hold them side by side
it's that they are more than Juck
deposed so it's been awesome and its
own great experience to work with all of
the instructors who shared their amazing
and Youthful and energetic
perspectives and we explored a new
format in a new way we're going to
process the proceedings of the lectures
and the
discussions
plus any final submitted question and
answers through the syllabus website
bring that together into a Open Access
publication of some kind so for people
who are interested in that kind of
editorial or curatorial work the active
inference Journal is for them and then
in 2024 and Beyond let's see where
active inference is see where social
Sciences
are and
hopefully as people are interested
in take it from there we threw a many
fun ideas but I guess we'll leave
it till then to find
out all right thank you everybody
bye